<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8174 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5905 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5905.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5906 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5906.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6335 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6335.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8633 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8633.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8915 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8915.xml">
<!ENTITY MODE6 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-ntp-mode-6-cmds.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="yes"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>

<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ietf-ntp-alternative-port-00" updates="5905" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title>Alternative NTP port</title>

    <author fullname="Miroslav Lichvar" initials="M." surname="Lichvar">
      <organization>Red Hat</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Purkynova 115</street>
          <city>Brno</city>
          <region></region>
          <code>612 00</code>
          <country>Czech Republic</country>
        </postal>
        <email>mlichvar@redhat.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2020" month="Oct" day="12"/>

    <area>General</area>

    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>

    <keyword>NTP</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document updates RFC 5905 to specify an alternative port for the
        Network Time Protocol (NTP) which is restricted to NTP messages that do
        not allow traffic amplification in order to make NTP safe for the
        Internet.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>There are several modes specified for NTP. NTP packets in versions
        2, 3, and 4 have a 3-bit field for the mode. Modes 1 (active), 2
        (passive), 3 (client), 4 (server), and 5 (broadcast) are used for
        synchronization of clocks. They are specified in <xref
          target="RFC5905">RFC 5905</xref>. Modes 6 and 7 are used for other
        purposes, like monitoring and remote management of NTP servers and
            clients. The mode 6 is specified in <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-ntp-mode-6-cmds">Control Messages Protocol for
        Use with Network Time Protocol Version 4</xref>.</t>

      <t>The first group of modes typically does not allow any traffic
        amplification, i.e. the response is not larger than the request. An
        exception is <xref target="RFC5906">Autokey</xref>, which allows an NTP
        response to be longer than the request, e.g. packets containing the
        Certificate Message or Cookie Message extension field. Autokey is
        rarely used. If it is enabled on a publicly accessible server, the
        access needs to be tightly controlled to limit denial-of-service
        (DoS) attacks exploiting the amplification.</t>

      <t>The modes 6 and 7 of NTP allow significant traffic amplification,
        which has been exploited in large-scale DoS attacks on the Internet.
        Publicly accessible servers that support these modes need to be
        configured to not respond to requests using the modes, as recommended
        in <xref target="RFC8633">BCP 233</xref>, but the number of
        servers that still do that is significant enough to require specific
        mitigations.</t>

      <t>Over time, network operators have been observed to implement the
        following mitigations:</t>

      <t><list style="numbers">
          <t>Blocked UDP packets with destination or source port 123</t>
          <t>Blocked UDP packets with destination or source port 123 and
            specific length (e.g. longer than 48 octets)</t>
          <t>Blocked UDP packets with destination or source port 123 and
            NTP mode 6 or 7</t>
          <t>Limited rate of UDP packets with destination or source port 123</t>
      </list></t>

      <t>From those, only the 3rd approach does not have an impact on
        synchronization of clocks with NTP.</t>

      <t>The number of public servers in the pool.ntp.org project has dropped
        in large part due to the mitigations (citation?).</t>

      <t>The length-specific filtering and rate limiting has an impact on the
        <xref target="RFC8915">Network Time Security</xref> authentication,
        which uses extension fields in NTPv4 packets.</t>

      <t>This document specifies an alternative port for NTP which is
        restricted to a subset of the NTP protocol which does not allow
        amplification in order to enable safe synchronization of clocks in
        networks where the port 123 is blocked or rate limited.
      </t>

      <section title="Requirements Language">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
          NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
          "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
          described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/>
          <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they appear in all
          capitals, as shown here.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Alternative port - update to RFC 5905">
      <t>The table in "Figure 6: Global Parameters" in Section 7.2 of <xref
        target="RFC5905"/> is extended with:</t>

      <texttable>
        <ttcol>Name</ttcol>
        <ttcol>Value</ttcol>
        <ttcol>Description</ttcol>
        <c>ALTPORT</c>
        <c>TBD</c>
        <c>Alternative NTP port</c>
      </texttable>

      <t>The following text from Section 9.1 of <xref target="RFC5905"/>:</t>

      <t><list>
        <t>srcport: UDP port number of the server or reference clock. This
          becomes the destination port number in packets sent from this
          association. When operating in symmetric modes (1 and 2), this field
          must contain the NTP port number PORT (123) assigned by the IANA. In
          other modes, it can contain any number consistent with local
          policy.</t>
      </list></t>

      <t>is replaced with:</t>

      <t><list>
        <t>srcport: UDP port number of the server or reference clock. This
          becomes the destination port number in packets sent from this
          association. When operating in symmetric modes (1 and 2), this field
          must contain the NTP port number PORT (123) or the alternative NTP
          port ALTPORT (TBD) assigned by the IANA. In other modes, it can
          contain any number consistent with local policy.</t>
      </list></t>

      <t>The following text is added to the Section 9.1:</t>

      <t><list>
        <t>The port ALTPORT (TBD) is an alternative port to the port PORT
          (123). The protocol and the format of NTP packets sent from and to
          this port is unchanged. Both NTP requests and responses MAY be sent
          from the alternative port. An NTP packet MUST NOT be sent from the
          alternative port if it is a response which has a longer UDP payload
          than the request, or the number of NTP packets in a single response
          is larger than one.</t>

        <t>Only modes 1 (active), 2 (passive), 3 (client), 4 (server), and 5
          (broadcast) are generally usable on this port.</t>

        <t>An NTP server that supports the alternative port MUST receive
          requests in the client mode on both the PORT (123) and ALTPORT (TBD)
          ports. If it responds, it MUST send the response from the port which
          received the request. If the server support an NTP extension field,
          it MUST verify for each response that it is not longer than the
          request.</t>

        <t>When an NTP client is started, it SHOULD send the first request to
          the alternative port. The client SHOULD be switching between the two
          ports until a valid response is received. The client MAY send a
          limited number of requests to both ports at the same time in order to
          speed up the discovery of the responding port. When both ports are
          responding, the client SHOULD prefer the alternative port.</t>

        <t>An NTP server which supports NTS SHOULD include the NTPv4 Port
          Negotiation record in NTS-KE responses to specify the alternative
          port as the port to which the client should send NTP requests.</t>

        <t>In the symmetric modes (active and passive) NTP packets are
          considered to be requests and responses at the same time. Therefore,
          two peers using the alternative port MUST send packets with an equal
          length in order to synchronize with each other. The peers MAY still
          use different polling intervals as packets sent at subsequent polls
          are considered to be separate requests and responses.</t>
      </list></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>IANA is requested to allocate the following port in the <xref
        target="RFC6335">Service Name and Transport Protocol Port Number
        Registry</xref>:</t>
      <t><list>
        <t>Service Name: ntp-alt</t>
        <t>Transport Protocol: udp</t>
        <t>Assignee: IESG &lt;iesg@ietf.org&gt;</t>
        <t>Contact: IETF Chair &lt;chair@ietf.org&gt;</t>
        <t>Description: Network Time Protocol</t>
        <t>Reference: [[this memo]]</t>
        <t>Port Number: [[TBD]], selected by IANA from the System Port
          range</t>
      </list></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>A Man-in-the-middle (MITM) attacker can selectively block requests
        sent to the alternative port to force a client to select the original
        port and get a degraded NTP service with a significant packet loss. The
        client needs to periodically try the alternative port to recover from
        the degraded service when the attack stops.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The author would like to thank Daniel Franke, Dhruv Dhody, and Ragnar
        Sundblad for their useful comments.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &RFC2119;

      &RFC8174;

      &RFC5905;

      &RFC6335;

    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      &RFC5906;

      &RFC8633;

      &RFC8915;

      &MODE6;

    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
